{"tossups": [{"question": "One general in this war was so successful at Civetot and Xerigordon that he ignored it to fight the Danishmends. While ostensibly fighting in this war, Emicho of Flonheim massacred Jews. Kilij Arslan lost the Battle of Dorylaeum during this war, and the counties of Tripoli and Edessa were founded in its wake. This conflict was originally intended to aid Alexius Comnenus, and it began after cries of \u201cDeus Vult!\u201d at the Council of Clermont. For ten points, name this crusade which resulted in the 1099 capture of Jerusalem.", "answer": "<b> First Crusade</b> (or<b> Prince\u2019s Crusade</b>; accept<b> People\u2019s Crusade</b> until \u201cEmicho\u201d is read; prompt on<b> Crusade</b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The name of this publication\u2019s founder, Walter Bagehot [BADGE-ut] is used as a pen name for one of its editorial columnists. This publication\u2019s name refers to an archaic name for support of free trade, as it was founded in opposition to the Corn Laws. Henry Kissinger once facetiously said that he no longer needs to think; instead, he just reads this London-based periodical. For ten points, name this weekly news magazine which provides commentary and analysis on current events, business, and politics, as well as a namesake branch of social science.", "answer": "The<b> Economist</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {}, {"question": "A painting protesting one form of this activity depicted it in a blue circle near the top; in that work by James Ensor, a bird bleeds on a man\u2019s head. In another work, two men watch this activity while standing against a red backdrop, while a woman turning away from this activity covers her eyes with gnarled fingers. Instead of watching this activity, two men in front of the artist\u2019s signature, one holding a sheet of paper, look directly at the viewer. For ten points, name this activity performed in Rembrandt\u2019s <em>The Anatomy Lesson</em> by Dr. Nicolaes Tulp.", "answer": "<b> dissection</b> or<b> surgery</b> (accept<b> vivisection</b>; accept The Vile<b> Vivisect</b>ors; prompt on The <b>Anatomy Lesson</b> of Dr. Nicolaes Tulp) (6) During this battle, the elderly civilian Judith Henry was targeted by artillery, and Edward Porter Alexander utilized \u201cwig-wag signalling\u201d to tell Nathaniel \u201cShanks\u201d Evans of an impending flank. This battle began after westward movement from Centreville resulted in skirmishing at Matthews Hill, and was decided when Joseph Johnston\u2019s reinforcements arrived via railcars. Picnickers were horrified by Irwin McDowell\u2019s defeat at, for ten points, what early victory for P.G.T. Beauregard, the first major battle of the Civil War? ANSWER:<b> First</b> Battle of<b> Bull Run</b> (or<b> First Manassas</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Robert LaFollete\u2019s suspicions regarding this event intensified after his Senate office room was raided. Following this event, Congress was granted the power to compel testimony by the Supreme Court\u2019s ruling in<em> McGrain v. Daughterty</em>. The perpetrators of this event took advantage of the Mineral Leasing Act. Edward Doheny acquired Elk Hills in this event, which led to the downfalls of Henry Sinclair and Albert Fall. Bribes for favorable leases of federal land were given out in, for ten points, what scandal that rocked the administration of Warren G. Harding?", "answer": "<b> Teapot Dome</b> Scandal", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Crescentii helped one person with this name gain power upon the ascension of Otto II. Another person with this name issued<em> Etsi du statu</em> upon receiving an embargo for writing<em> Clericos Laicos</em>. An Anglo-Saxon who took this name felled Donar\u2019s Oak, and a pope of this name declared that the church wielded two swords in<em> Unam Sanctum</em>. For ten points, give this name for a pope who fought with Philip IV and a saint who converted many in early 8th century Frisia and Germany.", "answer": "<b> Boniface</b> (accept<b> Franco</b> until \u201cEtsi\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this event, a Nightstawker helicopter entered a vortex ring state and damaged its tail rotor. Some participants in this event claimed they used \u201ccakebread\u201d or \u201ccrankshaft\u201d as a codeword instead of the controversial \u201cGeronimo.\u201d Contradictory accounts have emerged about whether or not the central figure in this event used women as human shields in his compound in Abbottabad. For ten points, name this May 2011 operation by Seal Team 6, codenamed Neptune Spear, in which the founder of Al-Qaeda was killed.", "answer": "the<b> death</b> (or<b> killing</b>, etc.) of Osama<b> bin Laden</b> (accept equivalents) Page 2", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In 1892, Isaac Bruce was falsely convicted of rape in this state but saved from hanging by governor James Hogg. After the murder of Lucy Fryer in this state, the accused supposedly pled guilty during a one-hour-long trial attended by 10,000 people; after four minutes of jury deliberation, the lynch mob castrated, burned, and desecrated of the body of Jesse Washington, an act later labeled a \u201cHorror.\u201d The aforementioned Bruce case stemmed from an incident during the Juneteenth holiday, which commemorates this state\u2019s 1865 abolishment of slavery. For ten points, name this state, the site of the 1916 Waco Horror.", "answer": "<b> Texas</b> <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This ruler sent a punitive expedition against the Singhasari Kingdom on the island of Java. Though he managed to establish suzerainty over the Kingdom of Pagan, he was repulsed at the Battle of Bach Dang by Tran Hung Dao. After the death of his older brother, this ruler waged a destructive civil war against his youngest brother Ariq Boke in the Toluid Civil War. The remnants of the Southern Song Dynasty were defeated by this man at the Battle of Yamen. The capital of Xanadu was owned by, for ten points, what founder of the Yuan Dynasty, a prominent Mongol emperor?", "answer": "<b> Kublai</b> Khan (or Yuan<b> Shizu</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In this war, one side\u2019s headquarters was destroyed in the Battle of Holy Ground. Benjamin Hawkins failed to adequately prepare for this conflict, in which the Spanish governor armed one side at Pensacola. Peter McQueen and William Weatherford instigated the massacre of Fort Mims in this conflict, which was ended by the Treaty of Fort Jackson. American forces became involved in this war following the Battle of Burnt Corn. For ten points, name this 1814 Native American civil war involving the Red Sticks faction of one of the Five Civilized Tribes.", "answer": "<b> Creek</b> War (accept<b> Red Stick</b> War before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During a bout of mental instability, this leader abdicated in favour of his son Louis I, but retook the throne after Louis\u2019 death less than a year later. Attempts to retake parts of Italy by this ruler\u2019s minister Giulio Alberoni led to his defeat by the War of the Quadruple Alliance. Despite the objections of Archduke Charles of Austria, this ruler ended up succeeding the last Habsburg Charles II. For ten points, name this first Bourbon King of Spain, whose rise to the throne was the subject of the War of Spanish Succession.", "answer": "<b> Philip V</b> of Spain", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A cryptic letter written during this scandal notes \u201cThe aspens will already be turning. [...] Come back to work - and life.\u201d In this scandal, classified information was leaked by State Department official Richard Armitage, possibly as retribution for the \u201cWhat I Didn\u2019t Find in Africa,\u201d op-ed opposing the invasion of Iraq. Lewis \u201cScooter\u201d Libby was found guilty of obstruction of justice for his role in this scandal, which forced the resignation of its central figure. For ten points, name this 2003 scandal in which the wife of Joseph Wilson was publicly \u201couted\u201d as a CIA agent.", "answer": "Valerie<b> Plame</b> affair (accept<b> Plame</b>gate or anything that mentions Valerie<b> Plame</b> in any way)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler refused to convert to Islam because he could not give up alcohol, which he called \u201cthe joy of our lives.\u201d This ruler forced Rogneda to marry him during his war with his brother Yaropolk. During the revolt of Bardas Phocas, this man helped Basil the Bulgar-Slayer crush the revolt by sending six thousand experienced soldiers. This man built the Church of the Tithes after his marriage to Byzantine princess Anna, after which a mass baptism in the Dnieper River occurred. For ten points, name this ruler who converted the Kievan Rus to Christianity.", "answer": "<b> Vladimir I</b> (or<b> Vladimir the Great</b>; or<b> Saint Vladimir</b>; or<b> Vladimir Veliky</b>; or<b> Svyatoy Vladimir</b>; or<b> Vladimir Svyatoslavich</b>; prompt on Vladimir)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Belgrade\u2019s Red Star Stadium\u2019s nickname was inspired by this venue, which is officially named for a journalist who campaigned for its construction, Mario Filho. This venue is named for the native birds that occupied the location where this stadium was built. In this stadium\u2019s \u201cblow,\u201d Uruguay defeated the host nation 2-1 in the finals of the 1950 World Cup. Germany defeated Argentina in overtime at this sporting venue, which will host both the opening and closing ceremonies for the 2016 Summer Olympics. For ten points, name this site of the finals of the 2014 FIFA World Cup, a large soccer stadium located in Rio de Janeiro.", "answer": "<b> Maracan\u02dca</b> Stadium (or Est\u00b4adio do<b> Maracan\u02dca</b>; accept Est\u00b4adio Jornalista<b> Mario Filho </b>before read; prompt on \u201cBrazil\u2019s )", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This composer\u2019s only cello sonata, written in G minor, was dedicated to Auguste Franchomme. This composer\u2019s Opus 10 and Opus 25 include a G-flat major work with rapid triplets in the right hand, and another written in response to the November Uprising. This composer was the first to use the term\u201cballade\u201d for instrumental music, likely inspired by the poetry of Adam Mickiewicz. The \u201cBlack Key\u201dand \u201cRevolutionary\u201d Etudes were written by, for ten points, what Polish composer of many mazurkas and polonaises?", "answer": "Fr\u00b4ed\u00b4eric<b> Chopin</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>In</b><em><b> Howard\u2019s End</b></em><b>, Helen Schlegel claims this piece represents \u201cgoblins marching across the universe.\u201d E.T.A. Hoffman wrote a glowing review of this piece, whose third movement begins similarly to the last movement of Mozart\u2019s (+) Great G minor symphony. This piece is quoted in every movement of a piano sonata whose movements are named for famous New England authors. William Ives\u2019 (*)</b><em> Concord Sonata</em> musically quotes, for ten points, what symphony that opens \u201cG, G, G, E flat,\u201d a motif described as \u201cfate knocking at the door,\u201d that was composed by Ludwig van Beethoven?", "answer": "Ludwig van<b> Beethoven</b>\u2019s Symphony No.<b> 5</b> in C minor (Beethoven not needed after mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The perpetrator of this event used a pseudonym based on Star Trek, Robert D. Kling. This event led to the passing of AEDPA. The perpetrator of this event carried an envelope containing pages from the</b><em><b> Turner Diaries</b></em><b> and cited a passage from John Locke about the</b> <b>right to (+)</b> <b>kill those who take away liberty. This event was supposedly motivated by the</b> <b>Ruby Ridge incident and Waco siege, and it employed an altered Ryder truck. It was the (*)</b> deadliest attack on American soil before 9/11. For ten points, name this terrorist attack carried out by Timothy McVeigh the Alfred P. Murrah federal building.", "answer": "<b> Oklahoma City bombing</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Henry Graham regarded it his \u201csad duty\u201d that he and Nicholas Katzenbach were ordered to break up this event. The man who performed this event had earlier \u201c[tossed] the gauntlet before the feet of tyranny\u201d in a speech supporting this event\u2019s goal. Unexpectedly, (+) Dave McGlathery did not arrive at the Foster Auditorium to attend this event, which opposed the actions of Vivian Malone and James Hood. John F. Kennedy ordered the (*) </b> National Guard to stop this event, whose perpetrator had promised \u201csegregation today, segregation tomorrow, segregation forever\u201d. For ten points, name this June 11, 1963 act of opposition to the integration of the University of Alabama, in which George Wallace literally obstructed a civil right.", "answer": "<b> Stand in the Schoolhouse Door</b> (propmt on descriptions of George Wallace preventing the integration of the University of Alabama before \u201cUniversity\u201d is read) Page 10", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One monument to this battle was the finish line for the marathon at the 1960 Summer Olympics. This battle was preceded by clashes at Turin and Verona, where Ruricius Pompeianus was killed. The loser of this battle misinterpreted the statement of the (+) Sibylline books that \u201can enemy of Rome would perish.\u201d It took place at an endpoint of the Via Flaminia. The winner used a military standard, the Labarum, supposedly after (*) </b>seeing a vision of a cross with the words \u201cin hoc signo vinces\u201d in the sky. That winner later converted to Christianity. For ten points, name this battle in which Maxentius was defeated by Constantine near a structure spanning the Tiber River.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Milvian Bridge</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Stanley Stein founded</b><em><b> The Star</b></em><b> to raise awareness about these people, while living in a place established for these people in Carville, Louisiana.</b><em><b> The House is Black</b></em><b> is a film about a village of these people in Iran, founded by Farah Pahlavi at Behkadeh Raji. King (+) Baldwin IV of Jerusalem was one of these people, who lived in Kalawao County, overseen by the Board of Health, during the reign of Kamehameha V. Father (*) </b> Damien served in a colony on Molokai that hosted, for ten points, what sufferers of a chronic infection by a mycobaceterium, otherwise known as Hansen\u2019s Disease, who suffer from skin lesions?", "answer": "<b> leper</b>s (accept people who suffer from<b> leprosy</b>) Page 11", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<em><b> The Wall Street Journal</b></em><b> called this case \u201cThe Decision Everyone Won.\u201d Archibald Cox\u2019s oral argument in this case noted that he was a Harvard graduate. This case was instigated</b> <b>when a white (+)</b> <b>medical school applicant was rejected from the medical school at Davis,</b> <b>though his scores were higher than some minorities who applied. Lewis Powell wrote this case\u2019s opinion, which was affirmed in (*) </b> <em>Grutter v. Bollinger</em>. For ten points, name this 1978 Supreme Court case that upheld affirmative action, but ruled that racial quotas in university admissions were unconstitutional.", "answer": "(Regents of the) University of California v.<b> Bakke</b> (accept in either order)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The Zakerzonia colloquially referred to the area west of this line. A 1919-1921 war over disputes over this line was ended by the Peace of Riga, which gave one country almost 200</b> <b>kilometers of land east of this line. At the (+)</b> <b>Yalta Conference, this line was formalized</b> <b>as one country\u2019s eastern border. This line was crossed from the east on September 17, (*) </b>1939 per the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact by the Red Army. For ten points, name this line demarcating the border between Poland and Russia, named after the Viceroy of India who drew it.", "answer": "<b> Curzon</b> Line ", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>In this year, the SS</b><em><b> Philadelphia</b></em><b> was destroyed while it was docked in harbor in a\u201cGreat Fire.\u201d A Coinage Act of this year approved the minting of the first federal (+) gold dollar coin in American history. In this year, massive numbers of people either traveled overland, crossed the Isthmus of Panama, or undertook a dangerous (*)</b> sea journey around Cape Horn to arrive at places like Mariposa and Placerville. For ten points, name this year in which large numbers of miners traveled to California during the gold rush and, like a San Francisco football team, were nicknamed for this year.", "answer": "18<b>49</b> (accept<b> 49</b>ers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}